Hi everyone, thanks for joining us. My
name is Robert. I will be your host.
This is Georgia O'Keeffe, Flowers and
Abstractions, our latest art history
program. Thanks so much for joining us.
And these are a few examples of some of
the fabulous and amazing Georgia
O'Keeffe paintings we'll be talking
about tonight that refer flowers and
abstractions. My name is Robert. A
little bit about myself, I'm Richie from
Detroit, Michigan. I was an art history
major in college at the University of
Michigan. I spent the first two years of
my career working at the Detroit
Institute of Arts and George O'Keefe,
one of my favorite artists and my
favorite color is blue. Blue is my
favorite color. And we also have our
good friend Patty joining us. Hi Patty.
You want to introduce yourself? And for
those who may not know, what's your
favorite color?
Yeah, I'm Patty from um Portsouth, New
Hampshire. And my favorite color is
quite prominent in this presentation.
It's uh Georgia O'Keefe's embrace of
various reds.
All right. Awesome. Well, we'll be on
the lookout for red and blue and purple
and pink and anything else um you have
in mind. So, thanks Patty. Thanks for
joining us. So, um you've been on this
program once before and we'll get
started kind of officially in just a
moment. any particular things you um
like about Georgia O'Keefe's flowers and
abstractions or any things you recommend
people be on the lookout for? Yeah, her
her flowers and abstractions more than I
mean I love everything that she's done.
I I admire her partly because she every
genre she's tackled she does in a very
um distinctive way that sticks with you.
Um the flowers and abstractions though
have a kind of effect where I often feel
like I'm literally just sinking into the
um the painting. I mean it it it it's
just very embracing
um to me and sometimes there's a sense
of vertigo with some of them depending
on what I'm looking at. Oh, okay.
Awesome. Well, thanks Patty. I
appreciate that and thanks so much for
joining us. Um sometimes Brad joins us
but he's on vacation tonight so he won't
be able to be here. Um same thing for
Harry. He's also on vacation, but that's
okay. You have Patty and myself, and
we'll give you our undivided attention.
So, George O'Keefe, she was born way
back in 1887, and she lived a long life.
She passed away in 1986, and this is the
second of a four-part series we're doing
on Georgia O'Keeffe. The first part, um,
we just played the kind of overview for
a few minutes ago. It was called Georgia
O'Keeffe, the New York Years, or you
could also maybe call it George O'Keefe,
the Early Years. Um, if you missed that
program, there's a recording of it on
our YouTube channel. I sent the link out
for that um, in along with the Zoom
information if you're watching us live.
And if you're watching the recording of
this, you can always go back to our
YouTube channel which is called
Washington DC History and Culture.
Thanks to all the 1.3 million plus
people that have watched our program
since the beginning of COVID. Gee, has
it been that long? Wow. Holy cow. Um, so
anyway, part one was George O'Keefee,
the early years or the New York years.
Um, this is part two today be talking
about flowers and abstractions. And then
part three, which we don't have a date
yet for this, but it'll be coming soon.
It's Georgia O'Keeffe, the New Mexico
years, and that'll be coming shortly.
And then the fourth part will be George
O'Keefe's home and studio tour. So you
can be on the lookout for that.
All right, a little bit about George
O'Keefe. Hold on for one second while I
tweet something on my computer.
All right, George O'Keefe. She was
what's known as an American modernism
pioneer. Uh she was part of the avant
guard. We'll be talking about what that
is a little bit later. Um so if you
think about modern painting in America,
George O'Keefe pioneer in that regard.
Um, she trained entirely in the United
States, which if you're not familiar
with um the history of a lot of artists,
you might think, "Oh, okay. Well, what's
the big deal?" So many artists uh
before, during, and since George
O'Keefe's lifetime at some point in time
have gone off to their um Europe and
studied there, the great masters and
things like that. And she never did. She
stayed um entirely in the US, at least
for her kind of initial upbringing, so
to speak, as an artist. She did later on
travel throughout the world, but her
training was entirely in the US, which
is unusual for someone uh particularly
from that era. The subjects that she's
most known for, flowers, abstractions,
New York cityscapes, and New Mexico
landscapes, but not sexuality. We'll
talk about why that is a little bit
later. And then her style, um George
O'Keefe's painting is very unique, very
distinctive. Um, and some of the reasons
why she used really bold colors as Patty
was mentioning talked about the red and
other colors and a lot of variety of
colors. Sometimes the profile artist you
can see easily what their favorite color
is. Um, not so much for her. She really
used the whole rainbow. Um, she also
used magnified shapes and simplified
details and juxtaposition. So you can be
on the lookout for that. She was married
to photographer and modern art promoter
Alfred Stigas. And she's one of the
world's great artists, not just a great
woman artist or a great American artist
or anything like that. Just a great
artist, period. So, we'll go talk why in
just a moment. All right. Our first
trivia question for the night. How many
paintings did George O'Keefe think make
or create? What do you think? Was it did
she make 10 paintings or 37 paintings or
289 paintings or 5,642
paintings? What do you think? The answer
over 2,000 paintings. She was really
prolific and she lived a long life and
she was very active as an artist during
her entire career. Now, unfortunately,
we're not going to be able to see all
2,000 plus paintings of George
O'Keefe's, but I did pick a few
highlights. And so, I pulled 60 or over
60 George O'Keeffe paintings that
focused on the subjects of either
flowers and or abstractions.
All right, here's the first one. Would
it be fair to say that she is among the
artists that established a distinctly
American type of painting? Oh yeah,
definitely. Just because she's such a
pioneer in the in the um genre like of
modern art and her art is just so
distinctive. I mean, you think about all
the artists there have been over
throughout the course of history and her
artwork is just so unique. It's really
amazing that she was able to kind of
carve out her own um niche, so to speak.
But yeah, that's a great point, Patty.
her real pioneer um in American art
because we don't really have time to get
in this particular topic but before
artists like Georgia O'Keeffe came along
Europe were was where all the great
artists were Monae and Van Go and people
like that the old masters before them
and it took artists like George O'Keefe
really to make America uh one of the
great art um say locations in the world
so great point Patty appreciate that
all right so we'll look at her artwork
in mostly a chronological order. Not
completely, but a little bit. Um, and
I'll show you where these paintings are
located at. Perhaps they're near your
home or where you might be visiting at
some point in time in the near future.
You go check them out in person. So,
this is at the Georgia O'Keeffe Museum
in Santa Fe, New Mexico, uh, which has a
fabulous collection of her artwork. And
this is called Teapot and Flowers from
between 1903 and 1905. It's a still
life. And wow, look at this. She painted
this when she was a teenager. Um they
think she was somewhere between 16 and
18 uh when she painted this. So she was
in the public school system when she did
this particular one. And I always like
looking at these artworks of early
artists like okay can you kind of see
the uh signs of things to come? So very
talented in that regard.
And then let's jump ahead a little bit.
If you want to know more about Georgia
O'Keeffe's earlier life or years or
career, um you can check out our
previous program. But Georgia ends up
meeting the photographer Alfred
Stiglets. And to many he's not a
household name per se, um the way George
O'Keefe is, but that being said, he was
a really important and influential
modern art photographer and he also was
a modern art promoter. So he had an art
gallery in New York. He was hosting uh
artworks by different modern artists and
he really um sought for the community in
general to embrace not only photography
as an art form but also modern art. And
there's a photo of him from 1915.
And he ends up meeting Georgia O'Keeffe
in New York City. She ended up uh she
was there on a trip. She ends up going
back to Texas where she was living. If
you didn't know that, George O'Keefe
lived in Texas um during two stints of
her lifetime. Um, but her and O'Keeffe
start this correspondence and he
essentially in so many words tells her
like, "Listen, if you want to be a
professional artist, you need to come to
New York City. This is where all the
action is taking place. Um, and you're
probably not going to be able to make it
as a professional artist um, living in
the Texas panhandle." And so she thinks,
"Oh, that's probably good idea." So she
moves to New York in 1918
the summer and O'Keeffe posed for many
photographs by her then uh friend George
O'Keefe. Um although things eventually
turned into a romantic relationship and
then later on they would get married.
That whole uh romance is a whole another
story for another day. And there's the
young George O'Keefe. And look, she's
sitting in front of some plants and
flowers making her artwork.
All right. So, what I thought I would do
is I broke up the artwork into
kind of like categories. And I like to
look at the art this way because while
it is great to see one individual
painting, sometimes you can get a little
bit more u appreciation or see things um
and you're looking at a group of
paintings together. And so like for
instance, these are early abstractions
that George O'Keeffe did. And if you
look at these seven paintings, you can
see quite a few similarities, but you
can also see quite a few differences. So
let's go look at these. And wow, look at
these fabulous colors. Um, you know, if
you were to look at this like, well,
gee, what color is Georgia O'Keeffe's
favorite? H, I don't know. She's using a
lot of different colors.
And this one is not far from where I'm
at, the Aean Carter Museum of American
Art in Fort Worth, Texas, which has the
largest number of Georgia O'Keeffe
paintings in the Lonear State. So if
you're in Texas and you like George
O'Keefe, come down to the Aean Carter
Museum of American Art. This is called
Series One, number one from 1918. It's
an abstraction, of course, and it's got
a lot of really great colors and shapes,
and you'll frequently see this with
George O'Keefe's artwork. She titles
them um as part of a series. So
something to be on the lookout for.
And then what exactly is abstract art? I
feel like that's a term where most
people know what it means. Um but like
what's the official definition? I think
most people if they see abstract art,
they can point it out, but what's the
official definition? It's art that does
not attempt to represent external
reality but seeks to achieve its effect
using shapes, forms, colors, and
textures. You can see that here. And
another definition of abstract art. Art
that uses the visual language of shape,
form, color, and line to create a
composition which may exist with a
degree of independence from visual
references in the world. So, we'll go
with independence from visual reality.
That's what abstract art is.
And you can remember those words and use
those the next time you're at a party
talking about art or some similar
function. Um, so yeah, really beautiful
painting with the great colors and
shapes.
Here's another one also at the Georgia
O'Keeffe Museum. It's called Blue Line
from 1919. Again, focus here on colors
and shapes
as opposed to depicting visual reality.
I think she uses both to
Oh, what was that, Patty? We lost you
for a second. You said I heard you say
you think she uses both.
Oh, hold I think Patty's having a
technical difficulty, but she'll be back
in just one moment. Um, all right,
Patty. Well, let me know when you get
back on. Let us know when you get back
on.
Here's one at the Philadelphia Museum
Art. It's called Red and Orange Street
from 1919. This was actually painted in
New York uh while she was living there,
but it was a painting that she did of
her memories of living in the Texas
panhandle when George O'Keeffe lived in
Amarillo, Texas, if you know where that
is. She was really um amazed by the sky
of the western United States and also
the storms that they had there and the
mountains and uh trains would run
through there and she was really
fascinated by that. So she ended up
making a lot of paintings
of her time there, including this one,
Red and Orange Street, 1919.
Hold on for just one second. I have to
tweak something on my computer.
Patty, can you hear me? Okay,
I can hear you now.
The ghost of Alfred Stiglets making you
muted.
So, let's see. You were um I heard you
say something about both and then you
cut out. So, I think we were looking at
this painting maybe uh the one before, I
think. But um she uses both color and
line to create a a sense of kinesis in
in these paintings. I think Oh yeah,
that is an excellent point. Thanks. I
appreciate that. Someone is asking if
she used um oil paints or acrylics or if
she could also include watercolor. She
did early on her career do a lot of
watercolor paintings. When she met
Stiglets, he essentially told her, "You
know what? serious artists don't use
watercolors, Georgia. And so from that
point on, she uh mostly did oil paint.
And then acrylic is more of like a
modern art kind of thing, like a little
bit later in the art world, so to speak.
Um but she did use a little bit
different formats, but almost all these
paintings are in oil. Um let's see. Oh,
here's another one. This is also from uh
memories of when she lived in Texas, but
it was painted in New York. Uh so it's
kind of strange. She goes to New York um
after living in Texas. It's almost kind
of like she's homesick for the Texas pan
and the landscape. She does a series of
paintings, not just these two, but
several others of the sky and the storms
and the mountains and the trains and all
that kind of stuff out there.
And that sense of kinesis is is very
very different from her New York period
because that is so solid and present.
Oh, sorry. I had my screen paused. Sorry
about that. Um, here was the painting
itself.
Thanks for the heads up.
Here's the full view.
Thank you, Carolyn Sharon. Appreciate
that.
And this is at another great museum in
New York, the Whitney Museum of American
Art. Music Pink and Blue number two. So
again, this has to do with the titles
where she would do these series of
paintings and there'd be number one,
number two, number three, number four,
etc. Another great abstraction with
colors and shapes. And this refers to
art and music. You might not know this.
George O'Keefe was a big music lover.
And she was really interested in kind of
the relationship between the visual
artists or the visual arts I should say
and music.
And for many Vanguard artists in the
early 20th century, music offered a
model for expressing nonverbal emotional
states and sensations. Georgia O'Keeffe
was fascinated with what she called,
quote, the idea that music could be
translated into something for the eye.
End quote. But her references to music
in the titles of her paintings derived
equally from her belief that visual art
like music could convey powerful
emotions independent of representational
subject matter in music. Pink and blue
number two. The fluid forms imply a
connection between sight and sound while
also suggesting the rhythms and
harmonies that O'keefee perceive in
nature.
Someone's asking what I mean by kinesis.
And this would be a good time to connect
with what you you just uh had up there.
The the sense of movement and flow and
um that it's just not a static thing.
And that commentary really sort of ties
that up. This was also the period that a
lot of the um distinctive forms of
American music including country and
jazz were being developed.
Yeah. And I think for a lot of people
they would never really make that um
connection. But uh it is kind of amazing
that these artists whether they're
visual artists or musical artists or
literary artists are all kind of working
in tandem so to speak.
And there's the filia. really love the
colors on this painting. Really
fabulous. And then again, just look at
these forms. I mean, if you had never
seen this painting before, um, and
someone asked you who made it, I would
think a number of people would maybe
guess George O'Keeffe.
Just a very unique and distinctive
style, which again is really incredible
when you think about the number of
artists there have been over the history
of art. And for someone to be able to
carve out their own niche, so to speak,
and create something that's very unique
to them, that's pretty extraordinary.
Here's another great one. This is blue
and green music.
Christina just put into words what I was
think trying to uh figure out a way to
articulate, but um what did she about um
let me let me find it now because I
thought I was going to remember it. Hold
on. Um oh, her shading is so tactile.
Yes. And what is tactile? What does that
elaborate for people that may not know
uh what that means? Especially since we
have people joining us from outside the
US that might not be uh native English
speakers. I think that's part of what um
makes me sometimes feel like I'm sinking
in it. Yeah. You you can almost touch it
or you can follow it or
it it's more alive than just sitting
there on a canvas. Do you know what I'm
saying? Yeah. just flat paint on a
canvas. It's like something you can
touch. Yeah. All right. Very good. Thank
you. Appreciate that.
And then here's again that quote from
Georgia Keefe where she's exploring
quote the idea that music could be
translated into something for the eye.
So how about that? So I don't know. I
can almost uh picture now George O'Keefe
at home and she's listening to music and
she's getting ideas and then going and
make uh paintings like this. I have this
painting is one of my sentimental
favorites because it was the um cover of
one of my art history books in college
on modern art. So there you have it. Um
let's see. And again really incredible
with the colors and the shapes and the
forms and the lines. A sense of dance. A
sense of what, Patty? A sense of dance.
Oh yeah, a sense of dance. Right.
Exactly. Yeah. Movement and all that
kind of stuff.
And then this is for our friends down in
Houston. Uh, the Museum of Fine Arts,
Houston has a great collection of George
O'Keefe pennies. Well, gray lines with
black, blue, and yellow from 1923.
Another abstraction focusing on colors
and shapes.
This one reminds me of her painting of
the Brooklyn Bridge. Oh, yeah. Oh,
that's an interesting connection. Well,
that cathedral sensation, you know, the
colors almost like stained glass. Uhhuh.
Yep. Michelle's pointing out a strong
sense of rhythm in her work. I think she
might have been successful in what she
was trying to do.
And here you have it. So again, when you
look at these seven paintings, now she
does a lot of abstractions throughout
her career, and we'll see some later
abstractions that she did which look um
a little bit different. Um but yeah,
here you go. seven great George O'Keeffe
early abstractions and you know you also
have to remember at this point in time
abstract art wasn't as um commonplace
uh as it is now if you talk to just
regular people most people know what
abstract art is and not to say that she
invented abstract art but art from this
period the late teens um and then in the
early 20s abstract art really hadn't
been around uh to this degree um for
that extended period of time so she's
really a pioneer in that regard. Any
particular um final thoughts, Patty, on
the early abstractions? Well, yeah, it
was like way before say the ones that
tend to be more familiar now like um
Warhol and Jasper John's and um uh
Jackson Pollock and Yeah. Jackson
um just I mean she's coming out of
nowhere with this which is again which
makes it even more amazing. Yeah,
exactly. Which is funny because I always
frequently hear people say um oh I don't
like modern art which you know that's
fine that's fair enough but um you know
maybe I think maybe sometimes when
people say that they might be referring
to like more contemporary art um as
opposed to like say art like this
because traditionally in art terms
modern art means like anything from like
I don't know the past 100 or 150 years
and usually contemporary art means like
past art from like the past say I don't
know few decades. Yeah, Christine was
just pointing out that in these
abstractions,
there's a very feminine aesthetic. Um,
which you you wouldn't necessarily say
about her New York paintings or her uh
desert paintings.
Oh, yeah. That is a great um point. And
which is interesting because like why is
that? I mean, I would maybe think, well,
it doesn't have harsh lines maybe, but
there are a lot of lines on her artwork.
Um, but there also a lot of curve linear
forms
and then the colors are um just really
amazing and fascinating.
All right, well, let's continue on. Um,
here's a cool painting. It's called
Plums from 1920. This one's in a private
collection, meaning like an individual
person owns this. So, I mean, wow.
Imagine coming home from work and you
know having this on your wall at your
house. That would be pretty cool. Um and
again it's a still life and but we're
seeing the emphasis on the colors and
the shapes of the plums. And there our
favorite colors are seen together,
Robert. Yeah, there you go. Red and blue
Patty and Robert coming together for
their love of the plums painting, which
is ironic because I do love this. It's
such a It's such a rich um both colors
are rich and and yet the connection
between them is even more rich. Yeah.
They're um you know those are different
colors but yet they're very uh
compatible in this painting. It's
interesting. Yeah. And that is one thing
that's neat about plums that they do
have different colors. I mean every
thing. Yes. Velvety is another good
description of her use of color. Mhm.
And then we'll be talking about a place
called Lake George, New York. And um if
you're not familiar with the geography
of New York City, I think when most
people when they hear New York, you
think New York City. Um this is a little
different of a place. This is upstate
New York. So Lake George is over here.
And Georgia O'Keeffe ends up spending a
lot of time there because Alfred
Stiglets and his family had a summer
home there. And so they would vacation
up there for weeks and months. on. Then
in the summer, George O'Keeffe ends up
spending a lot of time there because
she's in this um uh romantic
relationship and later on marriage to
Alfred Stiglets. And so she ends up
making a lot of paintings in Lake
George, New York, including this one,
Trees in Autumn from 1920 or 1921.
And more great, fabulous colors.
See that? This is extraordinary because
if you're someone who's lived in the
northeast, the Appalachian area or um uh
New England, this is not the typical
representation of autumn leaves. This is
just something from a different world.
Yeah, that is excellent. I mean, yeah,
because I mean that's one of the things
that that area of the country is known
for, just the beautiful fall colors and
this is a little bit different.
She's giving us her own unique style and
vision. Um, let's see. The museum, the
placard for this painting at the museum
says, "A vibrant canvas of a large
orange red tree against purple white
hills and a blue sky. Surrounding the
main red tree are areas of yellow color
on the left and a green fur tree on the
right.
So, that's pretty cool.
Now, Georgia O'Keeffe, uh, again, we're
talking tonight about flowers and
abstractions. Some of her paintings of
flowers are in fact abstractions,
including these ones. And what makes
these flower paintings abstractions?
Well, um, they have very simplified
forms. So, they cut out a lot of the
details. uh their magnifications,
meaning if you're looking at them up
close, um there's also this really close
cropping, which means there's you can't
see the background or anything like
that. And then of course also the
vibrant colors. So let's look at some of
these. This is the George O'Keefe Museum
in New Mexico. Series one, white and
blue flower shapes from 1919.
And you're going to see this over and
over again, this uh idea of
magnification where you think of looking
at something through a magnifying glass
um as opposed to say looking at it from
like a distance. Um and then because of
the magnification and the close cropping
and things like that, it makes these
artworks, I wouldn't say they were
completely abstract. Um, now maybe if
you were seeing this for the first time,
you might not know what it is, but when
you look at the title and then start to
consider uh this in the context of other
works that she did, I would maybe call
this semi abstract.
And what did her husband Alfred Stiglets
think about her artwork? Well, he was a
big fan of hers and a big promoter of
hers. And he called this uh say vision
that George O'Keefe had of her style a
new natural feminine essence.
And then it's funny because if you were
to uh like walk up and ask random people
on the street like what they know about
George O'Keefe, I wouldn't think it
would be like the first thing that would
come to people's minds, but something
you hear over and over again. Oh yeah,
her pictures are like of erotic stuff
and things like that. And um she was
actually kind of put off by that. Uh she
said in a quote, "When people read
erotic symbols into my paintings,
they're really thinking about their own
affairs." And kind of how this got
started in my opinion was um Stiglets
took nude photographs of George O'Keeffe
and hung them in his art gallery, which
was really shocking at the time. uh
nudity wasn't uh as commonplace as it is
now. And then after that, George
O'Keeffe ends up making all these flower
paintings and people uh men uh just
like, oh, you know, nude paint, nude
photographs, uh paintings of flowers, uh
must be something erotic going on there.
And it was funny because Steve Litz was
a like a real marketing guy, uh also in
my opinion. And he's like, hey, you know
what? If people think that that's fine,
it's going to sell more paintings. Um,
but George O'keist really thought that
kind of like diminished her artwork and
that's not what she was all about and
she was got annoyed by that because that
really kind of took wind and became like
a thing that people are even still
talking about today. Um, so kind of
funny the the contrasting idea between
George O'Keefe wanting to be a purist
and you know she's making this art and
people should look at it just for art's
sake and Stevens is like hey if they
want to read erotic stuff into it so be
it. makes her artwork more popular and
more likely to buy it. So,
Christine is making a point that there's
a difference between sensual and erotic.
Erotic like narrows it down to specific
areas. Yeah. Um Oh, yeah. No, that is a
great point. That is actually probably a
better word to use, sensual instead of
erotic. And and the sensuality comes
from both the curve linear, but also the
way she shades the colors. um real again
really has that sensuality to it. Yeah.
No, that's a great point, the two of
you. So, thank you very much. I
appreciate that.
This one's at the Pennsylvania Academy
of Fine Arts.
Here's Patty's favorite color, red. And
again, another flower abstraction. With
the uh magnification, it does make it
somewhat abstract. If I had that
painting in my house, I might never
leave my house.
Wow. Well, that's impressive. Yeah.
I'm falling into it. And I'm sure it has
something to do with the red, too.
JP, I just got the idea we should do a
program of nothing but red paintings,
like all the best uses of the color red
throughout history. We'll have to work
on that. Um,
yeah. Well, yeah. Now that I think you
do that for a lot of colors would
probably
[Music]
do black. You could talk about sneak
some Oh, I was going to say if you
wanted to talk about black, you could
sneak some mayonnaise things in there.
Well, which brings us back. We were
gonna say Petty, sorry I interrupt you.
Forever. How many colors do you use to
make white?
Oh, yeah. Exactly.
And this one's at the Whitney Museum of
American Art.
Here's one for our Mid-Atlantic friends
at the Baltimore Museum of Art. Pink
Tulip from 1926.
And again, the magnification, the close
cropping, the limiting of the details.
You can kind of see um some patterns
when you look at her artworks in groups
like we are now.
And you know, you also have what Mchuan
would have been uh later talking about
the the medium.
The the colors she uses changes the
total response to the to the painting
with the shapes, the the shapes and the
presentation.
Some of her colors are hot and others
are would be categorized as cool. Mhm.
So, um, if you were to like see one of
these paintings in a museum hanging on
the wall, kind of take it in and but
when you look at it like, oh, okay, wow,
look at these four paintings that George
O'Keefe made around the same point in
time in her career, the same kind of
style. And again, you really see kind of
some patterns of things that she's
focusing on.
All right, let's continue on. Here are
some patunias.
Patunia number two from 1924. This was
painted at Lake George, New York. And
it's another one of the several series
that George O'Keeffe did.
There's several others from the same
time, but we'll show you this one.
And this is Patunia's from 1925. Also
from Lake George, New York. I had to
give a shout out to my amazing wife,
Michelle, because this is her favorite
George O'Keefe paintings, which is not
surprising because purple is my wife's
favorite color. And hey, if you like a
particular color or you know someone
that does, you know, they have um note
cards of George O'Keefe's paintings or
framed prints and things like that, so
you can be on the lookout for your
favorite color or perhaps favorite color
of someone you know. This is at the D
Young Museum of Art in San Francisco.
And then here's the museum display. So,
sometimes it's really neat to uh see how
museums get creative in their displays
of their artwork. And so, here's some
actual flowers in front of the painting.
You can compare and contrast the real
thing with George O'Keefe's painting. So
nicely done here. Yeah, I was hoping you
were going to have this one in here. It
I just love this. Yeah, I just Why don't
more people do this? I guess probably
the time and effort involved.
And then let's zoom in and we'll look at
the painting in quadrants. So here's the
full view and then we'll zoom in and
look at it in quadrants. So here's the
top left.
And again, that magnification concept,
you know, it's funny when you zoom in
the painting like this, like, oh, this
actually could be a painting just like
itself, just this quarter. Um, because
it looks so similar to other things that
she's done. Here's the top right. And
again, these wavy curve linear shapes.
And then I also really like the great
colors. I mean, yeah, this is all
purple, but look at all the different
shades of purple. Like Patty was saying
about the color uh what was it you said
about the color white? We've talked
about that before. I don't remember the
exact he used to to make white snow
came up I think and but I've always
remembered that because I thought that
was a great way to get into this whole
idea of painting versus trying to color
trying to make something look real art
and bloom is saying yes
and then
close-ups of the bottom
And there you have it.
Um, another reason why I wanted to show
this particular photo is uh this idea,
and we'll talk more about this later
because there's a one or two quotes that
George O'Keeffe um has about talking
what she's trying to do. Look at the
size of this painting. So um I don't
have the exact dimensions here but you
know flowers are essentially pretty
small usually. Um these paintings are
much much bigger. So she's really uh
expanded the size and the scope uh of
these flowers so that we can look at
them more closely detailed than we could
be if we were just looking at the
smaller flowers in real life. And then
also too this display does really a
great job of just showing you all the
different u shades of purple and
different colors.
and she's encapsulated many of those in
her painting.
That's almost part of what makes or
gives me this sense of falling. It's
like you're taking in the the the
painting and yet you have to keep going
deeper and deeper because the shades
keep changing. And I think that may be
part of that sensation is that it just
keeps drawing you further in. Yeah, I
think so, Betty, because I don't find
myself like this. I just keep looking at
it. My eyes kind of roaming around. Look
at all these different shades of color.
Oh, look at that. Oh, no. Look at that.
Oh, no. Over here.
And so it gives it it it adds to that
whole sense of um dimension and
movement.
Yeah. Yeah. It's not as um static as
some still life paintings are.
You would not call this a still life.
Yeah. Right. In the traditional sense.
No. Because it is very different. The
plums. Yes. The flowers. No. Oh, yeah.
The plums. Um, so, you know, a lot of
artists are uh struggling artists.
That's kind of the um uh when we think
of artists, we tend to think of people
oftentimes um you know, struggling.
George O'Keefe was very successful u
during her lifetime. She was extremely
popular. She was self-sufficient. She
sold a ton of paintings. Um so, even
back in 1927, she had her first uh
museum exhibit. It was actually at the
Brooklyn Museum. So for our friends in
New York, Brooklyn was very proud of the
fact that they uh were the first museum
to host a Georgia O'Keeffe art exhibit.
Um so great distinction for them. So
she's um popular and successful while
she's alive and of course that continues
on um since she's passed away. This
painting was at the first museum exhibit
that she had in Brooklyn and then the
painting ended up joining the collection
of the Brooklyn Museum. So you can go
see it in person if you're in New York.
Black Pansy and Forget Me Knots from
1925.
This one is in Washington DC, the
Smithsonian American Art Museum.
Great shades of yellow here. And again,
that close-up detail
and the simplified forms.
How about I just draw away from the
screen and I'm trying to figure out why
it like antifreeze there. There's an
acidic sensibility to this one because
of the green and yellow. I I am amazed
that I noticed it, but it I literally
pulled myself back from the screen.
Well, and how about this quote from
Georgia O'Keeffe? Color is one of the
great things in the world that makes
life worth living to me. So, you can
really get a sense that she um loves
color. Uh and it's interesting when you
read letters that she wrote or quotes
from her uh just how often she talks
about color like over and over and over
again. It kind of reminds me a lot of
Vincent Van Gogh. If you read his
letters, he also talks a lot about
color. It would have been uh fascinating
if the two of them ever could have met
and had a discussion on color.
Oh, she might have killed him
probably,
but it would have been interesting
nonetheless.
Vincent meets Georgia. Hey, how you
doing? Yes, both of them were trying to
achieve a sort of truth that would not
necessarily
occur to a lot of other people. I like
yellow, too.
All right. So, then she does this other
um series of artworks which I'll call
the black abstractions. And again, um
it's always cool to look at artwork and
go to a museum and you see a painting.
But if you were to see one of these on
the wall, oh, that's unusual. Um but
then when you see it kind of in the
context of other ones that she did and
kind of see some things, patterns and
trends and things like that. So, black
abstractions.
So, it wasn't all yellows and reds and
purples for her.
And this is interesting because it has a
great contrast between the black with
all the colors that we've seen
previously. Some 1926.
This one jazz. What's that, Patty? This
one almost screams jazz. Not just this
one, though. The array.
Yeah. I mean, well, the date, don't you
think? That's cool. Um, well, she I'm
not really an expert on jazz. I don't
know. Oh gosh. Sometime we have you have
to look at that. Um, Ken Burns one.
Fabulous. You know, that's cool. And I
mean, hey, we talked about George
O'Keefe and the music. So, this is the
Whitney Black and White 1930.
And wouldn't it have been the heyday of
Jazz moving into the cities during the
the migration? Oh, yeah. You know, and
she's living in New York during this
time, so I'm sure she was getting her
fair share.
Harlem. Yep.
So, um yeah, again, just really think
these are fascinating, particularly when
you think of, wow, we just ended up
seeing all these paintings of all this
rainbow of colors. Um, and then at this
point in time, she's uh doing these
series of black and white paintings. And
I'm only showing you a handful of these.
She did several others um from the same
time frame that are a similar style. And
so just imagine all these black and
white abstractions.
Any other thoughts on these before we
continue on? Well, I'm looking at the um
the nice juxaposition of the curve
linear with the sharp um white and again
I I look at that and I think trumpet
it's like you know I mean it's like
there comes that trumpet making that
point right there and it I I just love
the way she she just surrenders herself
to to these images and colors. It would
be hard to imagine anyone not liking
color if they use all colors because
most artists again if you think of Van
Go you think of that blue and that
yellow.
But George O'Keefe you cannot restrict
her to any given color and that's across
her career.
Oh yeah and like Renoir we talk about
him in the red hair models and all that
stuff and Manise uses a lot of black.
So, uh, let's see. Here's a famous one.
It's the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New
York, Black Iris,
and she's capturing nature's abstract
forms where she's magnified this tiny
flower and allows viewer to see it up
close in detail.
The irises are so fragile, too. Yeah.
And there you go. the real thing on the
right and the Georgia O'Keeffe
representation on the left.
I didn't put the full um museum placard
in the um presentation, but the the
placard talks about the the sensual
curves and soft texture of this painting
and then again kind of enlarging it so
that we can look at great detail. And
this really interesting colors. is kind
of the um the combination of the grays
and the purples and the blacks and all
that stuff. Black iris and so this one's
her fave.
Okay, that's cool. And you know, black
iris a little bit different of a flower
just because it's a darker uh than the
average flower. I think myself, maybe a
lot of other people when you think of
flowers think of brighter colors
oftentimes.
Here
we go back to the still life. The
Philadelphia Museum of Art, Peach and
Glass, 1927.
Here's the Museum of Modern Art
Abstraction in Blue from 1927.
And so one of the things about
abstraction is in my opinion if you ask
people uh like what kind of paintings
does George O'Keeffe make? Usually in my
opinion um the two things that people
think of with her flowers and these New
Mexico landscapes. But as you can see
she did a lot of abstractions and that's
one of the reasons why she's really
considered one of the pioneers of modern
art. And so here's a great example. This
is not a flower uh per se or it's not a
Mexico landscape, but it is a kind of a
classic example of modern art, which is
why it's in the collection of the Museum
of Modern Art.
And
one of the sensations of this one is
it's unique in that you almost feel like
you're getting two completely different
perspectives of the same whatever it is.
Do kind of like a Yeah, it's kind of
like a mirror image of of each other.
the two halves. Yeah. It's an amazing
accomplishment.
Yeah. And so this over on the right is
kind of what I was talking about a
minute ago. So again, when you think of
Georgia Keith, okay, she makes all these
beautiful paintings of flowers and she
made all these spectacular paintings of
the New Mexico landscape, which she did.
Um, but she definitely, you don't want
to type cast her as just a a painter of
flowers and New Mexico landscape. She
did a lot of other things. We saw all
the New York Cityscapes that she did and
we've seen she's done some still lives
and now she's um we're doing all these
abstractions etc etc. So you don't want
to type caster is just the painter of
flowers in New Mexico landscapes
although those of course were amazing.
And here's a quote from Georgia. I found
that I could say things with color and
shapes that I couldn't say in any other
way. Things that I had no words for.
Callelies.
When I think of calles, I think of Diego
Rivera. He made a lot of great Callie
things. But let's look at some by George
O'Keefe.
Completely different from hers. Yeah.
Oh, yeah. Exactly. Um, gee, I should I
should have held up um one or two of his
just as a like a compare and contrast,
but um we'll do that next time. But this
is the Oklahoma City Museum of Art.
Callie
number two. Um Callies, if you didn't
know, I actually researched this a
little bit. I they are really
spectacular to see. Uh they're imported.
They're not native to the United States.
uh they originated in South Africa and
was global trade took root. Cowies ended
up being shipped all over the world and
many artists have done paintings of
them. Very distinctive in appearance.
Here's another one. The Whitney from
1928.
And let's look at some more flower
paintings. Notice um we were looking at
some darker flowers a little bit
earlier. Notice these ones are all very
light colored. Now most of these
paintings are in chronological order,
but I don't want you to think like,
okay, she made all these black and white
abstractions and then she stopped and
then she made like light colored flowers
and then she stopped. Some of these have
like overlaps
uh during the time frame, but I'm just
kind of grouping them together just so
you can get an idea of u these different
kind of like thematic subjects of her
career.
Here's the Museum of Fine Arts in
Boston.
One of the things that's uh also
fascinating, George O'Keeffe talked
about uh in her writings how a flower is
very short-lived. Uh that's one of the
things that makes them uh precious to us
is they they don't last forever. But
contrast that with a painting like
George O'Keefe made and they're eternal
at least as eternal as long as the
painting is still with us. We comments
on on that whole idea of the fragility.
Um, somebody had mentioned that um, if
you plant flowers on your own, it's
almost each time you spend with it, it's
like a seeing a play again for a the
same play, but it's now very different.
You have a different experience of it.
Oh, that's neat. Oh, I never thought
about that, but that's really cool
representation.
And Philadelphia Museum Art.
These are cowies, but I thought I'd
include them in this section.
yellow cactus at the Dallas Museum of
Art
and the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.
White Iris.
That is so delicate.
Yeah. Isn't it just really incredible?
And here they are without the titles.
Can see which one is your favorite.
I think she's getting added to my list.
You know that question of who would you
have? What people living dead would you
like to have dinner?
This lady has a lot going on. Yeah. Oh
yeah. I would have a lot of questions
for her. I would just like to sit and
listen to her. Mhm. Oh yeah.
Of this section, this one is my
favorite. Although I might be partial
because I live in Texas, but I do really
like this painting. And um you know, as
amazing as these Oh. Oh, go ahead,
Patty. Oh, when you put it up, I
thought, "Oh, that's very Texas." Uhhuh.
Well, the other thing too, I mean, as
amazing as it is seeing these pictures
on the screen of your computer or in a
magazine, uh, just to go see these in
person, like I've spent a lot of time
looking at this painting in person and,
uh, just really amazing just to study it
and look at it. You know, people walk
by, oh, I like that painting, too, kind
of thing.
This is almost like a berry arbor, that
that really delicate one, you know? It's
it Oh, yeah. It's just gorgeous. Yeah.
Oh my lord. I love this one. Yeah, I do
too. It's really u I mean I would sorry
I keep saying that over, but I love this
one too. Yeah, these oriental poppies at
the Wiseman Art Museum, which is um not
a real well-known place for people
outside of the state of Minnesota. Um
but yeah, this is a really uh incredible
painting. I can't describe it that way.
Wow. Uh, and great contrast between the
orange and the black.
The contrast is eye popping. Phyllis is
saying, "Yeah, you can't take your eyes
off it." Like, this is another one. Were
in my house, I'd never be leaving. Oh,
yeah. It's just so stunning. Which is
funny because I mean, I don't dislike
orange, but it's not my favorite color.
And um, but I love this painting. And I
don't know what it is about the orange
and this I don't know if it's the
contrast the black or the different
shading but uh just really incredible.
And how about this quote? What is my
experience of the flower if not color
and she magnifies that color so you just
can't not know about it. Well, what do
you like about this one, Patty? Since I
haven't done a good job
that draws me to this one, there's that
sense of motion. There's that sense of
falling into that black center and just
being enveloped in in this vibrancy of
color that you can't not know about. If
if it's there, you know about and
that and the black centers kind of um
well, you know what I'm thinking about
as I'm talking is Alice and Wonderland
and falling down the rabbit hole. Oh,
yeah. There's a sensation of that that
that you're just like sucked into it and
you can't move away. So brilliantly
alive. Patricia saying
there's a lot. Oh, go ahead.
It's funny because one time, you've
probably seen these. They sell these
boxes of note cards that have artwork on
them. And one time when I was working at
Dutch Place Arts, I bought one of those
and it was um these George O'Keefe
flower paintings. And this particular
note card and I used them to give to
people like for birthdays and Christmas
or whatever. This particular note card I
never gave away. I just kept it because
it was so I was just thinking that while
you were saying I Oh, I would never give
that away.
Well, you read my mind. I never did.
Well, it's the same thing. You cannot
pull yourself. You cannot part from
this. I don't know what I'm trying to
say, but it's amazing to me that she at
any point stopped painting this. I would
just keep going and going.
Yeah. Well, here's an interesting
comment from Sandy. She says, "Contrast
life and death maybe with the colors
with the black." That's cool. I never
thought about that, but yeah, you might
be right.
And then, all right, so this is not
George O'Keefe. This is some other guy,
uh, Monae or something like that, but
anyway. Uh, no, just kidding. Uh, this
is a a famous painting by Monae at the
Met. It's Chrysanthemums from 1882. And
notice his depiction of some flowers.
Now, Monae also had a really long um
career and did all different types of
flower paintings, but um let's kind of
look at a painting by Monae and then a
painting by Van Gogh. This is one of my
favorites from him. This is at the
Creger Museum in Washington DC. This is
some carnations among other things. It's
from 1886. So, okay. So, you have Monae
and then you have Van Go and these are
both flower paintings.
And then you have Georgia O'Keeffe. And
you know, artists have been painting
flowers since the beginning of time. And
you not to say that they all look the
same, but it is it was a very um uh uh
frequent genre of painting. Say, and
then George O'Keefe comes along and wow,
look how different that is. And you
know, the Van Go painting is different
than the Monaet one. And the two of
these are different than other ones. But
that being said, just she has this very
unique style which is really incredible
when you think of the sheer number of
people that have painted flowers over
the course of time.
The left and center there's a sense of
objectivity
which is not a negative thing but the
one on the right there's a sense of
participation.
Oh, I see. That's a cool way to put it.
And um I've said this before but you
know whenever I show these kind of side
by side things it's not to say that like
one is better than the other. It's
really just to show you like, you know,
differences or comparison and contrast
between them. And kind of same thing
here. I love all three of these
paintings, but they're all very very
different.
Yeah. And and one when you say
participation there, that implies one's
own kinesis. There's movement happening
in in the south. Not that it isn't
happening with the Monae or the the um
Van Go. It's just that it's a more
objective
um
there's a disconnect between you and the
painting. And I don't mean that in any
negative way. It's just an objective
perspective.
Yeah. And I guess um another thing when
consideration with these two like this
is how these flower floral paintings are
usually done. They're flowers and
they're in a vase and they're indoors
and you can see like the whole vase and
all the flowers and then wow. Okay.
Look, this is something different. You
don't see the vase and you don't see the
whole flowers. It's this closeup. Uh,
and it's a very different uh different
approach that she came up with. Yes. One
of our viewers just made the point that
um the Monet and the Van Go remind her
of the early the 16-year-old George
O'Keefe uh still life with the teapot
and the yellow flowers that the style of
the time. You know, that is a great
point. Actually, let me go back to that.
I really like that point. Thank you for
mentioning that. Let's actually
um go back to that. Sorry, it'll take
just a moment.
Hold on. That was Nancy, I think, that
said that. Oh, thank you, Nancy.
Appreciate that.
Okay, so yeah, here we go. That's a very
again kind of very traditional style,
and you know, I like this painting a
lot. I mean, it's cool and definitely
way better than anything I'd ever be
able to do. But hold the thought for
this one and then we'll fast forward to
the um one that we're looking at. And
voila, here it is. Yeah.
And you know, God, this Oh, go ahead,
Patty. Oh, no. If you group the the
teapot one with the Manet and the Van Go
and ask people to pick out which is the
O'Keefe, I'm not sure a lot of people
would immediately know. Yeah, that is a
excellent point because I would agree
with that. Some people might not be uh
be so sure about that one. And you know,
God, this painting is so amazing. I'm
almost tempted just to stop the program
right now. Just let's look at this for
the rest of the night. But that being
said, we'll continue on because who
knows, maybe there's some Oh, I hate
that.
Um, all right. Well, let's look at some
leaves, which not exactly uh flowers,
per se, but kind of a similar, you know,
natural element type of thing. And here
are three great examples of her work in
this area. This is at a private
collection pattern of leaves. And look,
one of the leaves is ripped. How did
that happen? And you can kind of see
some comparison and contrast between the
leaves and flowers.
Art Institute Chicago yellow hickory
leaves with daisy
1928.
Christina was is making the point that
yellow is a hard color to blend.
Ah, you know that is a good point. Thank
you. Appreciate that. In the 1920s,
George O'Keefe began concentrating on
representing enlarged still life
elements. Although no more for her
flower painting, she frequently depicted
leagues inspired by the example she
found on her walks around Lake George
and upstate New York, where she summered
with her husband, Alfred Stevens between
1918 and 1928.
In yellow hickory leaves with daisy,
O'Keefe painted the leaves around the
small white daisy at lower center so
that they seem to be manting from the
flower.
That is
to my ironing um fallen leaves with
between two sheets of wax paper. I think
that was fourth grade. Oh yeah. Yeah.
Common common educational exercise back
then.
I'm kind of old, Robert. Well, no. I I
we did that, too. Fact. My mom probably
still has them in her attic.
Oh, lordy. Here you go. two yellow
leaves. The Brooklyn Museum of Art. That
is a great point though. You can if you
look at the yellows and and then in this
one she's even got the green there. It
would be hard to blend those and yet
she's very good at it. Yeah, that is a
great point. I mean, I have to admit,
I'm not an artist. I just don't like
art. But I would imagine that yellow has
to be if not the one of the hardest
colors to paint just because um the I
don't know the composition of it so to
speak. So yeah, great point there. Thank
you very much. Look at how many fights
Van Go had with yellow. Yeah, exactly.
So there you go. Leaves.
She had an advantage. She could probably
afford more expensive paints than he
could. Yeah, she did. She did have that
advantage.
All
right, here's another one that the
Dallas Museum art gray, blue, and black
pink circle from 1929.
And this is actually a painting of a
flower, but because it's such a close-up
magnification, it does look like an
abstract painting. Like if you didn't if
you didn't know the title of this or if
you weren't familiar with George
O'Keefe's artwork, you might not
initially know what exactly this is a
painting of. And there's definitely a
sense of whirlpool to it, you know. So
again, draw in
George O'Keefe's early abstractions,
though not as well known as her later
southwestern paintings, played a pivotal
role in the development of American
modernism. And again, this because
there's not a lot of uh as Patty
mentioned before, you know, this is
before Andy Warhol and Jackson Pollock
and all these other great uh American
modern artists. Great blue and black
pink circle is the culmination of
O'Keefe series, a body of abstract
drawings and paintings that she made
during the 1920s.
Oops, jumped too fast. All right, so
this is a series. Um, up until now, I've
been kind of showing you um, examples of
different series that George O'Keefe
did, but they've usually just been like
one of the paintings just in the sake of
time. Um, but this particular one, I
want to show the full series because
they're all together at the National
Gallery of Art in Washington DC. This is
the Jack and Pulpit series. Um, and so
imagine going to the museum and seeing
all five of these paintings side by
side, which is what you can do when you
go to the National Gallery of Art in
Washington DC where I used to live.
Well, I didn't live at the National Guy
Art, but I lived in Washington DC. And
here's the flower itself.
Very distinctive
form in nature.
I think it's a form of orchid and I
believe it's native to North America.
When I was young, this was considered an
endangered species. Oh, yeah. As as were
lady slippers.
And so here's George O'Keefe's paintings
of the flower.
Now, I kind of was disappointed because
I couldn't find a picture that had all
five of the paintings on the wall, but
how the museum is configured is there's
another one. The fifth painting is on
the left. This is kind of like an
L-shaped um section of the gallery, but
it is really amazing just to be able to
stand here and look at five George
O'Keeffe paintings of the same subject
done in different kind of versions um
all side by side.
It's funny because um this picture this
I so I took this actually picture myself
and it was funny because um I used to
get when I lived in Washington DC I used
to give tours of different things
including the art museum and I
distinctly remember this photo because I
took this picture and then like a few
hour like maybe like an hour later um a
friend of mine who came on the tour we
were standing outside the museum.
Wow. What do you think's gonna happen
with this COVID thing that's like
starting to be in the news? I don't
know.
That was that was the last tour I ever
gave the museum because everything like
shut down three or four days later. So,
kind of a funny a sentimental photo from
me. Um, but anyway, this really amazing
to go here and see these uh paintings in
person. Jack and Pulpit number two, the
magnified flowers. this is a series um
and kind of the the similarities and the
differences between these five
paintings. So, Caroline's correcting me.
She says it's from the Aram family and
not related to orchids, but so I Well,
thank you. But thank you, Carolyn.
That's what's cool about these programs.
A lot of smart people on these. So,
thank you.
And so why does Georgia paint flowers
like this? Well, here's a quote. So I
said to myself, I'll paint what I see,
what the flower is to me, but I'll paint
it big and they will be surprised into
taking the time to look at it. I will
make even busy New Yorkers take time to
see what I see of flowers. And so um she
had a lot of quotes kind of on this
similar uh theme. And she's talking
about how, you know, people are really
busy and they don't really stop to take
time to look at a flower for very long.
Um even though they're beautiful, but
yet she's going to make these big
paintings and it will really kind of
grab people's attention and get them to
stop and look at them. So really cool
that she did that. And so that's one of
the reasons why she made these big uh
magnified enlarged flowers because she
wants you to stop and take a look at
them as opposed to maybe more of a
traditional still life of flowers. This
is Christina's favorite by the way.
Which one? This one. Yes. Okay. Well,
you have good taste and it's really cool
one.
to go back to your point, Patty, would
be really um fascinating to uh just sit
and listen to her talk about these or
actually watch her make one or two of
these. was definitely not a shrinking
violet and I don't mean any pun by that
but as for her era and again she had
some advantages um that other artists
might not have um but she definitely was
not a shrinking violet
that that is extraordinary right there.
Yeah. Yeah, I mean it's hard to uh even
think that this is a flower if you
didn't know like may maybe if you were
familiar with George O'Keefe and you saw
this like oh and you know about like oh
okay well she does these magnifications
so that's a flower but if you just some
random person walked in the museum like
what do you think this is a painting of
uh I don't know the moon or a building
or who knows a street light there's
something otherworldly about it
yeah and just very unusual and again
here's the flowers in nature
And then here they are with her
paintings.
All right, let's continue on. Here's
another sideby-side comparison for you.
Great contrast of blue and black. This
one is at the Met.
And so in 1929, George O'Keefe ends up
going to New Mexico for the first time
and she just immediately fell in love
with it and makes all these pennies,
including many of the flowers there.
We have a program. The next Georgia
O'Keefe program we do is going to be on
New Mexico paintings, but it's going to
be more focused on like the landscapes
and things. Um, so, but I thought I
would include the flower ones that she
did there in this particular program.
There have been several um precursors
that make me think immediately of the
Gyson weed she did for who was it?
Helena Rubenstein.
Oh, um, yeah. Hold that hold that
thought. That's coming up in just a
little bit. But do you see it where that
do you see like the precursor or the
hint of of of how the gyms weed? I'm
wondering the commission came from
seeing some of these hints. Oh yeah. No,
that's a good a good question because I
mean again she was well known um during
this time. It wasn't like she was an
unknown artist. And hey, can you make
something that looks like that?
And then here's another quote kind of
what we were talking about before.
Nobody sees a flower really. It is so
small. It takes time. We haven't time.
And to see takes time. That's really a
great quote. Not just for this painting,
just uh art in general and life on a
grander scale. Everyone is so busy. Uh
we don't take time to what what's that
saying? Take time to stop and smell the
roses. Roses. Yeah. No pun intended.
Yeah. You have to take time to stop and
look at the flowers. That relates to
that idea of a play though, too. You can
see a play half a dozen times and find
different things in it. Yeah. Or, you
know, same thing like we're talking
about music. Listen to a song. If you
have a favorite song, you would listen
to it over and over again.
All right. Here you go. We were just
talking about this. So, yeah. Look at
these paintings. Oops. Sorry. Look at
these two. And then
how about these two? Yeah. And the
earlier one as well.
So this is at the Crystal Bridges Museum
in Arkansas, which was started by the
Walmart family. Gyson white flower
number one. And this painting was
purchased by Alice Walton for the
Crystal Bridges Museum collection. And
the purchase price was $44.4 million.
And that was even 11 years ago. I mean,
uh, imagine with inflation what $44.4
million would be today. But that was a
record price paid for a Georgia O'Keeffe
painting. And this was from her New
Mexico
home. She had these.
What's that, Patty? I said at that
price, I'll take two. Yeah. Right. said,
"Well, there are two kind of a similar
uh similar paintings that she did." So,
yeah.
And then here you go. George O'Keefe
Flower painting sells for
record-breaking $44.4 million.
I like that her paintings are um you
know they're all very similar but that
they're all very different. They're all
unique. I'm going to play a short video
from our friends at Sibies. But because
of copyrights I'm going to pause our
recording because I don't want to record
the video I'm about to play. So hold on
for one second.
All right, let's continue on. There's
the Volu.
And then here's a similar painting. This
is at the Indianapolis Museum of Art,
which also has a great collection.
Jimson from 1936. So, this is the
largest flower painting that George
O'Keeffe made. Her paintings um overall
are usually pretty good size. They're
not usually massive. Um but this
particular one is extremely large. It's
71 in by 84 in. And this is what Patty
was referring to earlier. This was a
commission that she received from
Elizabeth Ardan. Uh Elizabeth Ardan was
um opening up a salon in New York and
she liked George O'Keefe's artwork and
she asked if she could make a painting
specifically for the salon. And the
commission was worth $10,000
uh way back in 1936, which would be
$219,000
in today's money. So again, George
O'Keefe, a successful artist during her
lifetime. Here's the painting. And then
I'll show you a picture of it hanging in
the museum because
it's so large, but we'll see that in
just a moment. But again, this kind of
idea of taking, you know, I hate to call
a flower ordinary just because they are
so beautiful. But that being said, uh
you see flowers frequently in nature and
different places and she's transforming
the ordinary of the everyday flower and
do something extraordinary like these
paintings. And wow, okay, here it is on
the wall. Um, I was kind of disappointed
because I couldn't find a picture of a
person standing next to the painting um
to give you that context. But I mean,
this is a a museum wall and you can see
some people back here, but this is a
giant painting. Um, it's 7 feet wide.
So, yeah, imagine having this in your
salon or in your home or in your museum.
And again, great colors and shapes.
What's that, Patty? No, you know what?
never occurred to me before, but it's a
common theme in mythology. I had the
wrong u makeup maven. Um I said
Rubenstein is Ardan, but um
there there is that sort of um
suggestion of poison and beauty, you
know, together. And oh yeah, weed is a
somewhat toxic plant or halluc hall
hallucinogenic plant, but if you think
of I I can't think of one of the
specific myths right off, but there is
always that mystery of of um lethality
to to the pursuit of beauty. Oh yeah.
Well, that pursuit of like a lot of
things in the Greek Roman mythology.
Well, I'm I'm just thinking though,
Elizabeth Ardan commissioning a gyson
weed painting
um whether she was conscious of that
when she did. Oh, you know, I don't
know. That's a good question.
Good question.
So, yeah, Indianapolis Museum of Art.
Next time you're in the Hooser State and
go check that out. They have a great art
collection.
I'm glad you me. Somebody was asking.
Yes. And again, so the one on the right
is at the
museum in Indiana and the one on the
left is in Arkansas.
All right. Sunflowers.
Very popular flower.
George O'Keefe made several sunflower
paintings. These are just two of the
many examples.
Sunflower New Mexico number one from
1935. Cleveland Museum of Art.
And this one is in a private collection.
It's called Sun, a sunflower for Maggie.
And Maggie was George's friend Margaret
Johnson, as in the Johnson and Johnson
family.
[Music]
And Margaret Johnson um became friends
with George O'Keefe and gave her a
sunflower one day as a gift and she
decided to make a painting of it.
All right, Patty's favorite color, red.
[Music]
This is at the Aean Carter Museum of
American Art in Fort Worth again.
So, this particular painting is 10 years
earlier than the next one we're going to
see. I'm just grouping them together
because they're both great examples of
the bold and vivid color that is red.
By magnifying her botanical subjects,
O'Keeffe transformed the traditional
genre of stilllife painting into
something entirely fresh. Her studies of
plant life celebrate the dynamic colors
and patterns found in nature and also
commemorate her association with people
and places. She related the subject of
red kennas with her husband, the
photographer Alfred Stiglets. The
flowers blossomed in their garden at
Lake George, a resort town in New York's
Aderandac Mountains where the Stiglets
family owned a summer house.
And then here's one in Chicago.
This one is 10 years later. So the
previous was in 1927. This one's 1937.
And just two fabulous examples of
the color red.
Petty as a as a lover of the color red.
Any other thoughts on these two? That
that's one of my favorite combinations
is is that you know any shade of red
with the right shade of yellow?
Oh, I see. Okay, that's cool.
Well, if you're looking to pop out in a
crowd, you know.
Oh, yeah. They say if you're driving a
red sports car and you're speeding,
you're asking for trouble because you're
going to stand out.
And then um we saw this painting when we
were doing the New York program. It's
called Pink Dish and Green Leaves from
1929.
And the reason why I'm showing it here
is because
well, here's the full view first.
And if you look at the pink dish,
you'll notice it makes an appearance in
this painting, although from a different
perspective. So, okay, here's the pink
dish from the side view. And then here's
the pink dish but from up above with
some deranium leaves.
And it's a great uh combination of the
natural
form is in the deranium leaves and the
man-made form in the pink dish. And also
the difference uh between the shapes of
the dish and the leaves
and the art deco too. Yeah. Yeah. Great
point. Thanks Patty. I forgot to mention
that. But yeah, like you really get a
sense of the art deco um in this
particular one.
And it's almost like if you look at the
the original the painting, the New York
painting, it's almost like she was
going, by the way, coming attractions
of where she was going to be going in
that, you know, uh, art deco vase that
comes out of nowhere in shouldery New
York. Oh, yeah. Because I would think a
lot of people, well, maybe if you're
really familiar with George O'Keefe, you
might be like, "Oh, yeah, yeah, I can
see where this is a George O'Keefe
painting." But I would think for a lot
of people that maybe had never seen this
before, they might not uh immediately
recognize this is a Georgia key. That's
a great point about Yeah. Okay, here it
is, but coming soon. Here's another one
for you.
I should have put the one on the left.
I should have put the one on the right
on the left because that one actually
came first. But you get the idea.
And Christina, I think that isn't the
New York one already on video, the
YouTube. Yes. Uh, yeah, I posted the
link for it in the chat if Okay. And it
should also be with the Zoom link that I
sent out earlier. Um, all right. Let's
talk about some later flowers.
Later meaning like later in her career.
Museum of Modern Art, an orchid from
1941.
poppies at the Milwaukee Art Museum. I
like this painting a lot.
I mean, I like all of them, but some of
them um just really incredible. I'll put
this into Patty's category of if I had
this in my house, it'd be hard to leave
home.
[Music]
When you take a flower in your hand and
really look at it, it's your world from
the moment. I want to give that world to
someone else.
Oh, and I forgot to mention if you're
watching this live, the video that we
recorded, those were George O'Keefe's
words, but that was a actress that we're
reading. So, that wasn't George
O'Keefe's actual voice. Forgot to
mention that earlier. Um, and this is at
the McNay Art Museum, uh, museum that I
really like in San Antonio, Texas. So,
next time you're in San Antonio, don't
just go to the Alamo or the Riverwalk.
Go over to the McNay and see this
beautiful Georgia O'Keeffe painting. For
some reason, this one reminds me of
grapefruits.
Yes.
Although it's not a grapefruit, it's
pink and yellow holly hawks.
And again, this idea of okay, usually a
flower is something really small and you
put it in your hands. And then this is
an example. Okay, here's one of the
paintings. Um, and you can see these two
gentlemen are holding it. Um, and you
can see the size of it. So very
different. Uh, this flower that normally
fit in the hand palm of their hands. Um,
they've been enlarged. So we can kind of
look at it. So, thanks, Georgia.
Appreciate that. You wouldn't call her
her flowers posies.
Yeah. Mhm. Yeah. They're flowers,
but um if you look at this one, just
look at all the incredible detail here
and here. And then like, you know, we've
talked about the colors and the shapes
and the forms and the lines
and it the the fragility is set is
painted right in there. I I I don't know
how to explain what I'm trying to say,
but it's there. Yeah. Oh, yeah. No, I
know what you mean. And you know, that's
I again, I'm not an artist, just an
admirer of art, but that can't be an
easy thing to do because you really
don't see that um frequently in artwork.
Um, not at that scale.
And that looks very fragile to me. Yeah,
I would agree with that.
All right, there you go. Some later
flowers.
Now remember at the start of our program
we talked about these early abstractions
that George O'Keeffe did which these
were really unusual for the time. There
weren't other artists that were making
things like this. Um but Georgia
O'Keeffe makes abstractions throughout
uh most of her career. So okay so these
are some early ones
and then how about these later ones?
And yeah again you can see some
similarities but you can also see a lot
of differences. So again here's the
earlier ones. I'll hold that up for a
second just to kind of refresh your
memory.
And here's the later ones we'll look at.
This is blue a from 1959.
And look at so George O'Keefe born in
1887.
72 years old and still making great
artwork.
And she wasn't sitting down to paint
these. They're too big. Yeah.
Only one.
Do you have any idea what that's in
reference to? Only one? Uh, no. Well,
unfortunately I don't on this particular
one.
Interesting. It's the only one I don't
know that I just
it was yellow and pink. Number three.
A lot of these um landscapes or I should
sorry a lot of these abstractions she
got inspired by landscapes. Um whereas
some of the earlier ones it could have
been landscapes or flowers or this or
that. Um the later ones tend to be more
kind of inspired of like these large
scale outdoor places often times.
Christina was pointing out the first one
um had a massive amount of movement in
it. I would agree. No, the first one.
Yeah,
that one just moves. It really does.
Yeah, really incredible.
So, let me go back because I wanted to
show you the beginning one. Oops. All
right. So, here's the early ones. What
do you think, Patty? Early ones versus
the later ones. What do you think?
Um,
I think overall the the the slide I I
like the earlier ones, but I do love the
um upper right hand one on the the later
one, too.
Um, these just are so adventurous.
These by this you're like, "Oh, yeah. I
can recognize where she's coming from.
It's just it doesn't grab you in the
same way because the the earlier ones
would be kind of abrupt. Nobody wasn't
expecting them.
Yeah. And these are very kind of fluid.
And it looks like the scale is like she
it looks like she's trying to show you
something that's like bigger. Um not
that these are small. Um but these look
like a little bit more like closeup and
these seem to me like more kind of far
away. These seem more related to the
landscapes too, which would it would
they would have come after she had
already developed that period too.
All right, let's continue on. All right,
so this is not a photograph of George
O'Keefe, but this time frame was the
beginning of the jet age and travel
becomes more uh frequent and
commonplace. And did you know that
George O'Keefe loved to travel? She
visited uh many many different places
throughout the world and she actually
even got inspired to make paintings as
she was on airplanes looking out the
window because you know you're high up
above and you're looking down. And so
she did a whole series of paintings
essentially from an airplane window. Now
she wasn't making the paintings um while
she's flying the airplane but kind of
got inspired by the the flight and the
travel. And so this is above the clouds
one from 1962 or 1963. in these series
of paintings um from airplane views in
Georgia Key very wellraveled.
And then here's another one. This is the
Art Institute of Chicago Sky Above the
Clouds number four from 1965. This is
the biggest painting she made in her
career. It's 8 feet high and it's 24
feet long or wide. Wow. Um, it took her
a long time to work on this and again
inspired by her airplane travel. And
when she made this, she was 77 years
old. Wow. Amazing.
You know, she could have just been
sitting at home all day watching
cartoons and taking naps and stuff, but
no, she's making incredible art. I
painted a painting 8 feet high and 24
feet wide. It kept me working every
minute from 6:00 a.m. till 8 or 9 at
night as I had to be finished before it
was cold. I worked in the garage and it
had no heat, meaning the garage of her
home in New Mexico. Such a size is of
course ridiculous, but I had it in my
head as something I wanted to do for a
couple of years. And if you want to see
this painting in person,
it's at the Art Institute of Chicago.
George O'Keefe has a long connection
with the Art Institute Chicago. She
actually studied there as a student um
in her earlier days and lived in Chicago
and worked for a period of time as a
commercial artist. One of the things and
you can see a picture of here of her in
the bottom uh when the painting was
being installed at the museum. Georgia
O'Keefe frequently visited the art
institute Chicago and she donated a
number of her artworks to the museum
including this one. So and that went on
a ladder to be painting this. Yeah,
exactly.
Especially when you're that age. That's
what I'm think thinking. Yeah.
And then it's really neat because when
you go to the museum, u you come out of
the like the American Art Gallery, if
you're coming from up above and like
boom, this painting is staring you right
in the face. Or if you're downstairs,
you're going up to the American Art
Gallery. Um it's right here. And you
frequently see people stopping to, you
know, look at it or selfies or whatever.
And so just um sometimes the museum have
like different things uh going down
here. But yeah, I mean, look at the
scale of the painting next to this
dancer. So really, not only is it a
great painting, but the way the museum
is it on display is also really
spectacular.
I bet you there's not a lot of proposal
pictures though with this one.
Um, you know, I don't know. That's a
good point. I'll have to I might have to
look into that, Betty. Maybe. I'm not
sure.
Hey, let's get married and come fly away
with me.
queued up the Frank Sinatra come fly
away with me song. Yeah.
That is incredible though. Oh yeah. So
next time you're in Chicago, go check
that out. See, we're in the home stretch
for a program. Got a few more paintings
to go. How about this one? She baited
this when she was 85 years old for God's
sake. Another still life. and she was
really into found objects, meaning like
objects that she found as she was out on
her walks and traveling about. So, black
rock with blue sky and white clouds. And
you can see the rock here is on this um
pedestal which looks like it's a marble
column. And it's really uh interesting
uh differences between the rock and the
column and the sky with the clouds in
the background.
And all right, another one from the age
85 era. This is one of the last
paintings she did. So Georgia O'Keeffe
did this painting in 1972. It's one of
her last paintings. You can see she
lived to 1986. In her later years, she
essentially had to give up painting
because she was having too many uh
health issues with her eyes and uh her
arthritis and things like that, just
overall um health issues. God, 85 years
old. Um a lot of people don't even live
that long, unfortunately. But she is
alive and she's still making artwork,
but she lived for quite a few years
after this painting. But right around
this time, she pretty much had to give
up um making artwork, unfortunately. But
this one um is called the beyond which I
think is fascinating and you don't I
don't like to read too much into uh
artwork because you kind of get carried
away. But hey, the title of this and the
subject is she kind of maybe realizing
that gee I' have lived a long life. I'm
not going to be around forever. Um and
is there any kind of connection between
the two? I don't know. To look at it and
decide for yourself.
There's definitely a sense of transition
in it. Oh yeah.
Because in the words of my favorite art
history professor at the University of M
Michigan, Dr. Rick Axom, when you look
at art, you can see whatever you want to
see.
And true for this one as well.
Yeah, as Elizabeth is saying, it looks
like a horizon. That's as somebody who's
a coastal dweller, that reminds me of
ocean sky. Ocean horizon sky.
Yeah, that is a great comment. Thank
you. Appreciate that. I would agree.
That's what I think of when I look at
this one
because there's even, believe it or not,
there's a difference between the two
blues. The way they she puts them on the
canvas. They're just two different
things. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Very
different.
So, all right. We've been learning about
George O'Keefe. She was born way back in
and she passed away in 1986.
A very long life and long career. Um
this was um uh feedback from our
audience saying hey can you kind of
summarize some of these programs like a
few talking points like what are the key
things? So all right so Georgia O'Keefe
uh American modernism pioneer we talk a
lot about that influence she had on
modern art. really part of the avant
guard, meaning she wasn't just uh doing
traditional things. She was bringing
about change. Um she trained entirely in
the United States. You didn't hear
anything about her, you know, studying
in Paris. Uh the subjects, you know, the
flowers and abstractions are the most um
uh common things that we talked about
today, but she also did these New York
Cityscapes and then New Mexico
landscapes we'll talk about next time,
but not sexuality or should say
sensuality. um the style these very bold
colors there was a lot of different
colors we saw the magnified shapes and
the simplified details uh and we saw the
juxosition of the different objects in
their artwork she's married a
photographer and modern art motor outfit
Stiglets and one of the world's great
artist not just a great woman artist or
a great American artist just one of the
world's great artists period and then
this is the question. Did she did not
have children, right? One one of our one
of our viewers asked if she had
children. She did not, right? Yeah, she
did not have children, which um
interestingly enough, if you think of a
lot of the great women artists did not
have children. Freda Ko did not have
children. At least not any that lived.
Um and then Mary Cassat, she didn't have
children. Um Margaret Bourke White
didn't have. So, you know, these women
give kind of giving up the whole um
children thing to focus on their
careers. Interestingly enough, but a lot
of but but they were all stilling. They
were creating just not creating what
women are expected to create. Yeah.
Well, especially in that era, but you
know, a lot of famous men artist, male
artists didn't have children. The Van Go
didn't have children. So, um All right.
So, this is been a second part of a
four-part series. The first part was on
the early New York years. Um that was
part one. If you missed it, you can
watch it on our YouTube channel. This
one is part two. It's on flowers
abstractions. I'll this program is being
recorded. Um I'll post the recording on
our YouTube channel and I'll send out
the link, but um it's going to take me
at least a couple days to do that. So
bear with me for that. Um our YouTube
channel is called Washington DC History
and Culture and we have a sister channel
called Texas History and Culture. If
you're wondering why we have two,
because I used to live in Washington DC,
but now I live in Texas. That's why
that. Um, and then part three, which I
don't have the date for this, but it'll
be coming up pretty soon because I'm
almost finished with this one. It's
going to be called George O'Keefe, the
New Mexico Years. We're going to be
looking at all these really cool,
fabulous, and amazing paintings that
George O'Keeffe did while she was living
in New Mexico, the place she's most
closely associated with. And I have to
tell you, as a sneak preview, I've never
lived there, but I visited many times,
and New Mexico is one of my favorite
states. It's one of the most beautiful
states in America. And then part four,
which will be later on down the road,
will be George O'Keefee a online tour of
her home and studio. And wow, look at
this view out her bedroom window. How
would you like to wake up or go to sleep
at night with that view? And then look
at her house. Um, I always find it
fascinating. You know, artists, they
create all these amazing uh incredible
artworks. What do their homes look like?
you know, whether it's Freda Ko or
Claude Monae, and we've done programs on
the two of them in their homes, but this
time we'll be visiting George O'Keefe's
home, but I don't have a date for that
yet because still working on this
particular one. Um, and then um Van Go's
home, huh? What's that? I said no
program on Van Go's home. Um, well,
yeah, that's because he like lived in so
many different places and the home that
was most famous, the yellow house, blew
up during World War II, unfortunately.
But that would be neat to see um uh see
his stuff. Just FYI, we have some other
art programs coming up if you're
watching us live. Um we won't do this
forever, but for the time being, the art
programs all use the same Zoom link. So
just hold on to that and you can join us
then. But our program, next art program
is next Saturday, eight days from
tonight. It's going to be called Claude
Monae and Impressionism at the
Metropolitan Museum of Art. And then in
early July, mid July, we'll be talking
about George Caleb Bingham and the
American experience. And then in later
July, we'll be talking about the
American collection at my former
employer, the Detroit Institute of Arts,
which has this incredible collection of
American art, including this great
painting by John Singer Sergeant. So,
um, let's see. I'll play a couple short
videos in just a moment, but before we
do that, Patty, any final thoughts on
George O'Keefe?
Now, people are really um thanking you
viferously for this program. Um,
somebody said that they felt like they
knew a lot about Georgia O'Keeffe, but
were fascinated by the insights that
came up here. Oh, well, thank you. I
appreciate that. I couldn't do this
without Patty's amazing help. And of
course, we have our great audience. But,
thank you very much. I appreciate that.
What about George Ot's artwork? Any
final thoughts before we queue up those
final two short videos? I'll never not
be in love with her artwork. I mean, you
know,
it's just hypnotic. You it you can't
resist it. Yeah.
That said they hated her work.
You have to find one. Yeah. I wonder if
there are people that that because she
has such a broad range. How can you say
I hate Jojo Keefe? I mean like Freda Ko,
you would say, well, there's a
consistency to to her work. And of
course, she didn't live anywhere near as
many years and she had a lot of health
issues. But the I don't know how you
could resist this lady. You know, it's
funny you say that because I don't know
what made me think of this, but a long
time ago I worked for this guy and when
I first met him, one of the first things
he said to me was he was we were talking
about traveling to different places and
Paris came up and he's like, "Oh, I hate
Paris." You know, I've heard people say
like they dislike Paris or it's not
their favorite place, but just the fact
that he said, quote, "I hate Paris." And
like the anger in his voice, I just
thought was really unusual. Well, come
to find out that guy was like one of the
biggest jerks I've ever met in my life.
Well, that's I hate Paris thing was like
a real It should have been like a
warning sign. So, when you said like,
"Oh, I don't know how anyone could like
hate George O'Keefe." Like, yeah, I
would. You wouldn't think so. But then
again, maybe I should go ask that guy
that I used to work for. See, that's one
of the great things about getting older.
You could tell right away which people
weren't spending any time with. Exactly.
After after he said that, I should have
been on be and LinkedIn later that
night, but I stayed there for deal with
it for a year. Deal with the
negativities and sarcasm for a year
now. Yeah. I've actually had people say
to me, "God, you're so strange. If you
don't like something, you just forget
about it." And I'm like, "Yeah." Well,
yeah. There's there's so many other nice
um things to watch. So again, I'll post
the video. It take a little bit. Um I
thought why don't I do this? We'll close
out our program, but before we do, um
I'll ceue up previews of our next two
programs. So a short preview of the
Claude Monae and Impressionism program,
which we doing next Saturday evening. Um
it'll use the same Zoom link. And then a
quick preview of our George Caleb
Bingham, a great American artist that
some people might not be familiar with.
So if you're watching us live, stay
tuned. Um, we'll end the commentary now
and Patty, thank you so much once again
for joining us. Greatly appreciate all
the time you give to us and enriching
people's interest in art history. Thank
you. So, thanks everyone. Oh, I really
enjoy the company and and the co the
commentary is fabulous, too. Yeah. Oh,
yeah. I've learned so we've talked about
this before, Patty and I, but we both
learn and Brad too when he can join us
and even Harry, we all learn so much
from your great comments and interesting
insights. So, appreciate all the
comments from the audience. Let me